Every time we made contact with them, we kept serving them food, day after day, so we needed to grow. We moved into the big coliseum. 25,000 meals became 50,000 meals, became, all of a sudden, the biggest restaurant in the world. We were making close to 70,000 meals a day from one location alone. (Applause) Volunteers began showing up by the hundreds. At one point, we got more than 7,000 volunteers that were at least one hour or more with us, at any given moment, more than 700 people at once. You saw that we began creating a movement, a movement that had a very simple idea everybody could rally behind: let's feed the hungry. And we began making food that people could recognize, not things that come from a faraway place in plastic bags that you open and you cannot even smell. (Laughter) We began making the foods that people feel home. People in these moments, they had this urgency of feeling they are alive, that somebody cares. One meal at a time, it didn't only become something used to bring calories to their bodies, calories that they needed, but they needed something else. They wanted to make sure that you and you and you and you, that you were caring, that we were sending the message that we are with you. Give us time, we are trying to fix this. That's what we found every time we began joining the communities. Fresh fruit began coming, even when in FEMA, they were asking me, "José, how are you able to get the food?" Simple: by calling and paying and getting. (Laughter) (Applause) We began feeding people in San Juan. Before you knew, we were feeding the 78 municipalities all across the island. We needed a plan. One kitchen alone was not going to feed the island. I went to FEMA. They kicked me out with eight armored guards and AK-47s. I told them, "I want 18 kitchens around the island." Guess what? Three days ago, we reached our 18th kitchen around Puerto Rico. (Applause) People began being fed. Volunteers kept showing up. We never had any system to deliver the food, people would tell me. Sure, we had the system. The entire island of Puerto Rico was the perfect delivery system. Anybody with a truck wanted to help. Anybody going from A to B was for us the way to be bringing hope and a plate and a whole meal to anybody. We began finding amazing systems to do these food trucks, 10 amazing food trucks. We began learning not to use the place that needed the food, but the number, the number of the apartment: Lolo, a 92-year-old veteran that was surrounded by water. We began giving not only hope to people, but knowing their names, checking day after day, making sure that those elderly people will never, ever again feel alone in a moment of disrepair. And we began going to the deeper areas, places that all of a sudden, the bridges were broken, but we had to go, because it was easy to stay in San Juan. We had to go to those places that actually, they really needed us. And we kept going, and people kept waiting for us, because they knew that we will always show up, because we will never leave them alone. (Applause) The food trucks became our angels, and the food trucks kept sending hope, but we saw we needed more: Vieques and Culebra, two islands far away from the island -- somebody had to be feeding them. We didn't only bring food and make a hotel kitchen operation in Vieques and bring daily food to Culebra. We brought the first water purification system to the island of Vieques, where we could be filtering one gallon per minute. All of a sudden, big problems become very simple, low-hanging fruit solutions, only by doing, not planning and meeting in a very big building. (Laughter) And then we found creative ways. We needed helicopters. We asked. We got. We needed planes. We asked, we paid, and we got. We kept sending food to those places that really were in need. And the simple ideas just become powerful. Volunteers will go to the edges of the island. All of a sudden, it was a movement. The teams of World Central Kitchen will be received with prayers, with songs, with claps, with hugs, with smiles. We were able to connect in so many corners. When I tell you that even the National Guard began calling us because our national poor guy's guards, big heroes in a moment of chaos, they couldn't get a simple humble plate of hot food. And partnerships show up. Mercy Corps, HSI from Homeland Security, partnerships that they didn't happen calling the top. They happened in the hotel room, in the middle of the street, in the middle of the mountains. We saw that by working together, we can even reach more people. Partnerships that happen by logic, and the urgency of now is put to the service of the people. When we have emergency relief organizations, we cannot be planning about how to give aid a month from now. We have to be ready to start giving help the second after something happens. And children were fed, and all of a sudden, the island, while still in a very special moment where everything is fragile, we saw that an NGO like ours -- we didn't want to break the private sector -- that already, small restaurants were being opened, that somehow, normalcy, whatever normalcy means today in Puerto Rico, was happening. We began trying to be sending the message: we need to start moving away from the places that are already stabilized and keep concentrating in the areas that really need help. (Video): People of Puerto Rico, two million meals! José Andrés OK, let me translate this to you. (Laughter) Almost 28 days later, more than 10 food trucks, more than 7,000 volunteers, 18 kitchens ... we served more than two million meals. (Applause) (Applause ends) And you guys coming here to TED, you should be proud, because we know many of you, you are part of the change. But the change is only going to happen if after we leave this amazing conference, we put the amazing ideas and inspiration that we get, and we believe that nothing is impossible, and we put our know-how to the service of those in need. I arrived to an island trying to feed a few people, and I saw a big problem, and all of a sudden, the people of Puerto Rico saw the same problem as me, and only we did one thing: we began cooking. And so the people of Puerto Rico and the chefs of Puerto Rico, in a moment of disrepair, began bringing hope, not by meeting, not by planning, but with only one simple idea: let's start cooking and let's start feeding the people of Puerto Rico. Thank you. (Applause) Dave Troy: Go back out. (Laughter) DT: The public loves you. (Applause) Nate Mook: A couple of quick questions, because I think some folks would be interested to hear. So as you said, you came the first time, got on the ground, went to the government command center, started to have some meetings with people, and they weren't very receptive. José Andrés: This is great. This is how good my talk was. (Laughter) It's the first talk with a follow-up in the history of TED. I feel so good. (Laughter) NM: So tell us why, what were some of the challenges, and then when you noticed, they started coming to you to ask you. JA: We cannot be asking everything from Red Cross or Salvation Army. But the idea is, I donated before to those organizations, and they are the big organizations, and maybe the problem is that we're expecting too much from them. It's not like they didn't do what they were supposed to do. It's that the perception is that that's what they do. But all of a sudden, you cannot get into a moment like this and wash your hands, and you say somebody else is going to be picking it up. We had a simple problem that had a very simple solution. This was not a faraway country or the Green Zone in Baghdad. This was American soil, a beautiful place called Puerto Rico, with hundreds, thousands of restaurants and people willing to help, but all of a sudden, we had people hungry, and we didn't have a plan how to feed them in the short term. So yes, FEMA, to a degree, was thinking about how to feed the people. Red Cross didn't have the right answers, because Southern Baptist Church, the biggest food organization in America, my heroes, they were never called to Puerto Rico. When you see the Red Cross delivering food in America after a hurricane, it's Southern Baptist Church doing it. We didn't have that in Puerto Rico. Salvation Army came and asked me for 420 meals on a Wednesday rainy night for a local elderly shop. I love to help the Salvation Army, but in my world, they are the ones who are supposed to be helping us to answer those calls of help. Thursday morning is when I wake up super worried that actually we didn't have the plan to feed the island. And some people will say maybe you are making the problem bigger than it was. Well, we had hundreds and hundreds and hundreds and hundreds of organizations knocking on our door, asking for a tray of food, so if that's not proof that the need was real ... We cannot be feeding people in America anymore with MREs or something like you open and, you know, I was giving to this little cat a little bit of those same foods -- (Laughter) and then I gave them the chicken and rice we made, and they went for the chicken and rice. (Laughter) (Applause) They don't even eat that themselves. We can feed humanity for a day or two or five, but those MREs cost, like, 12, 14, 15, 20 dollars to the American taxpayer. It's OK for certain moments, during battle, but not to be feeding Americans for weeks and weeks and weeks, when actually, you can be hiring the local private business community to do the same job better, creating local jobs, helping the local economy to come back, and in the process making sure that everything was going to go back as normal as quick as possible. That's where we began cooking. You were there with me, and that's why we spent every single dollar we had in our credit cards. If AmEx is listening to this, please, a discount would be appreciated. (Laughter) Or Visa. NM: So what's the situation now? You know, it's been a month. You said there's been some improvements in San Juan and focus on the areas outside, but obviously there are still major challenges, and what's next? JA: There are. So what's next is we slowly began going down after, more or less, FEMA let us know that they thought they had everything under control and we were no longer needed, but you only believe everything so much. We moved from the big place you saw, 60,000 meals a day, to another one, as big, but more strategically located, also cheaper, where we are going to be making 20-25,000 meals a day, and then we are leaving four, five, six kitchens strategically located around the island, very high up in the mountains, in the poor areas. We got a lot of data. We know who is using SNAPs, who is using food stamps, the cards. We know who has them and we know who is using them. So in the parts of the island where nobody is using them, those are the parts of the island where we are going to be focusing our efforts. So it's amazing how sometimes simple data can give you a clue of who are the people in need. So we went to a town called Morovis. Beautiful. The best chicken restaurant in the history of mankind. You should all travel to Morovis. DT: Sounds good. JA: So I saw the chicken. We were bringing sandwiches. I stopped. I was with these Homeland Security officers. We ate the chicken. I left to drop these sandwiches in this other place called San Lorenzo. San Lorenzo was critical, because the bridge was broken, and so it was an island inside the island, a little community surrounded by water. Everybody told us, "It's a disaster down there." We dropped the sandwiches. I went back to Morovis, and I thought, you know, if it's a disaster, sandwiches is not enough. I brought 120 chickens, with yucca and with rice, and we went back to that broken bridge, we crossed the river, water up to everywhere. We arrived with the 120 chickens, we dropped the food, and the community were very thankful, but they told us, "We're OK, we don't need more food. We have gas, we have money, we have good food and our water is clean. Take care of the other communities around us that are in more need." You see, communication is key. In these scenarios, we can be relying on fake news or we can be having the real information that we can make smart decisions to really take care of the true issues. That's what we are doing. (Applause) NM: It was an amazing operation, and to witness it firsthand and to play a small role -- JA: You made it happen. NM: At its peak, I think you were up to about 150,000 meals per day, across the island, which is pretty incredible. And I think, at the same time, really sort of setting a model for how this can be done, hopefully, moving forward. I mean, I think that's one of the big learnings out of this -- DT: This is possible. You know, people can replicate this. JA: But I'm going to stop coming to watch TED Talks, because you've got ideas that anything can happen. (Laughter) And then my wife told me, "Man, you told me you were going to cook a thousand meals a day. I cannot leave you alone for a day." (Laughter) But I hope that World Central Kitchen -- you know, one thing we did I didn't say: I picked up the phone and I began calling people, people that I thought had expertise that could help us. So I picked up the phone and I called a company called Bon Appétit, Fedele. Bon Appétit's one of the big catering companies. They do food for Google and for arenas. They're out of California. They belong to a bigger group called Compass. And I told them, "You know what? I need cooks, and I need cooks that can do volume and that can do good, quality volume." In less than 24 hours, I began getting people and chefs. At one point, we got 16 of the best chefs that America can offer. You see, America is an amazing heart country that always is sending their best. What we've been learning over the years is that those chefs of America are going to be playing a role in how we are going to be feeding America and maybe other parts of the world in times of need. What we need to start is bringing the right expertise where the expertise is needed. Sometimes I have a feeling, like with FEMA, we are bringing the wrong expertise in the areas that it's not even needed. The people of FEMA are great people. The men and women are smart, they are prepared, but they live under this amazing hierarchy pyramidal organizational chart that everybody falls out of their own weight. We need to be empowering people to be successful. What we did was a flatter organizational chart where everybody was owning the situation and we all made quick decisions to solve the problems on the spot. (Applause) DT: Absolutely. Another round of applause for José Andrés. (Applause) (Cheering)
Cuando nos contactábamos con ellos, les seguíamos sirviendo comida a diario así que necesitábamos más lugar, y nos trasladamos al estadio Coliseo. Los 25 000 platos se convirtieron en 50 000, y de golpe pasó a ser el restaurante más grande del mundo. Preparábamos unas 70 000 comidas al día desde una sola ubicación. (Aplausos) Empezaron a llegar cientos de voluntarios. En un momento llegamos a tener más de 7000 voluntarios que trabajaban con nosotros como mínimo una hora o más, y en cualquier momento siempre había más de 700 personas trabajando a la vez. Y así empezamos a crear un movimiento con una simple idea a la que todo el mundo podía unirse: alimentar a los necesitados. Empezamos a crear platos que la gente pudiera reconocer, no como esa comida que viene de lugares remotos, en bolsas de plástico, que cuando las abres ni siquiera puedes oler. (Risas) Cocinábamos platos para que la gente se sintiera como en casa. En ese momento, esas personas tenían la necesidad de sentirse vivas, de sentirse queridas. Una comida, en ese momento, no solo era algo con lo que aportar calorías al cuerpo, calorías que necesitaban, sino que necesitaban algo más. Querían saber que todos se preocupaban por ellos, que les estábamos diciendo: "Estamos con Uds. Les pedimos un tiempo, estamos tratando de arreglar esto". Y eso es lo que nos encontrábamos cada vez que llegábamos a un sitio. Empezaron a traer fruta fresca, y en la FEMA me preguntaban: "José, ¿cómo consigues la comida?". "Fácil: llamas, pagas y la tienes". (Risas) (Aplausos) Primero, abastecimos San Juan. Sin darnos cuenta, alimentábamos a los 78 municipios de la isla. Pero necesitábamos un plan. Una sola cocina no alimentaría a una isla. Fui a la FEMA y ocho guardias armados con fusiles me echaron. Les dije: "Quiero 18 cocinas repartidas por toda la isla". Adivinen qué. Hace tres días abrimos la 18ª cocina en Puerto Rico. (Aplausos) La gente empezaba a sentirse nutrida. Seguían presentándose voluntarios. La gente me dirá que nunca tuvimos un sistema de reparto de alimentos. ¡Claro que lo tuvimos! La isla entera de Puerto Rico era el sistema de reparto perfecto. Cualquiera con un camión podía ayudar. Cualquiera que pudiera desplazarse de un lado a otro, era señal de esperanza y significaba un plato con comida para alguien. Desarrollamos sistemas increíbles para usar camiones de comida; diez camiones fantásticos. Empezamos a aprender a no usar el lugar donde la gente necesitaba comida, sino el número, el número de vivienda: "Lolo, veterano de 92 años, atrapado por el agua". No solo repartíamos esperanza a la gente, sino que sabíamos sus nombres, los visitábamos todos los días, asegurándonos de que esa gente mayor jamás se volviera a sentir sola en momentos angustiosos. Luego nos adentramos en las áreas más profundas, lugares donde, de repente, los puentes se habían caído. Pero había que ir, porque era fácil quedarse en San Juan. Debíamos ir a esos lugares que realmente nos necesitaban. Y seguimos adelante, y la gente seguía esperándonos porque sabía que apareceríamos, que nunca los íbamos a dejar solos. (Aplausos) Los camiones de comida se convirtieron en nuestros salvadores, siempre repartiendo esperanza, pero había que hacer más: Vieques y Culebra, dos islas lejos de Puerto Rico, necesitaban que alguien las alimentara. Repartimos alimentos y construimos una cocina en un hotel de Vieques y suministramos comida a Culebra. Además, construimos el primer sistema de purificación de agua en la isla de Vieques, donde podíamos depurar 3,7 litros de agua por minuto. De pronto, grandes problemas se volvieron muy simples, con soluciones fáciles, poniendo manos a la obra, sin planes ni reuniones en grandes edificios. (Risas) Y luego pensamos de forma creativa. Necesitábamos helicópteros: los pedimos y los obtuvimos. Necesitábamos aviones: pedimos, pagamos y los conseguimos. Así, seguimos distribuyendo comida a las zonas realmente necesitadas. Una simple idea se convirtió en algo poderoso. Los voluntarios iban hasta los extremos de la isla. De pronto, habíamos creado un movimiento. Los equipos de 'World Central Kitchen' eran recibidos con oraciones, con canciones, con aplausos, con abrazos, con sonrisas. Hicimos tantas conexiones en tantos sitios... Créanme cuando les digo, que incluso la Guardia Nacional nos llamó porque los pobres Guardias, grandes héroes dentro del caos, no tenían ni un simple plato de comida caliente. Y surgieron colaboraciones: la ONG filantrópica Mercy Corps, HSI, la sección de investigaciones de la Seguridad Nacional, colaboraciones que no surgieron por contactos en las altas esferas. Surgieron en una habitación de hotel, en medio de la calle, en las montañas. Comprendimos que, trabajando juntos, podíamos llegar a más gente. Colaboraciones que tienen una lógica, y donde la urgencia del momento está al servicio de la gente. Las organizaciones de ayuda humanitaria para emergencias no podemos pararnos a pensar cómo vamos a auxiliar dentro de un mes. Tenemos que estar preparados para actuar el segundo después de que algo suceda. Los niños estaban alimentados, y de repente, la isla, todavía en una situación muy delicada donde todo es frágil... No queríamos que una ONG como la nuestra destruyera el sector privado. Vimos que estaban abriendo pequeños restaurantes. Que de alguna manera la normalidad, o lo que se entiende por normalidad hoy en Puerto Rico, estaba volviendo. Entonces empezamos a comunicar la idea de que debíamos empezar a alejarnos de los sitios que ya estaban normalizados y continuar nuestra tarea en las áreas que realmente lo requerían. (Video) ¡Gente de Puerto Rico! ¡Dos millones de platos! Vale, permítanme que les explique esto. (Risas) Al cabo de casi 28 días, más de 10 camiones de comida, más de 7000 voluntarios, 18 cocinas... servimos más de dos millones de platos. (Aplausos) Y Uds., que vienen a TED, siéntanse orgullosos, porque ya conocemos a muchos de Uds., y Uds. son parte del cambio. Pero el cambio solo sucederá, si después de abandonar la conferencia ponemos en práctica las ideas y el entusiasmo que tenemos y creemos que nada es imposible, y ponemos nuestro conocimiento al servicio de aquellos que lo necesitan. Llegué a una isla para darle de comer a unas cuantas personas y vi que había un gran problema, y de pronto, la gente de Puerto Rico vio el mismo problema que yo, e hicimos una sola cosa: nos pusimos a cocinar. Así, los puertorriqueños y los chefs de Puerto Rico en un momento de desolación, empezaron a sembrar esperanza. Sin necesidad de reunirse o de hacer planes, tan solo con una simple idea: vamos a cocinar y a alimentar a la gente de Puerto Rico. Gracias. (Aplausos) Dave Troy: Vuelve, vuelve. (Risas) DT: El público te quiere. (Aplausos) Nate Mook: Solo un par de preguntas, que creo que a la gente le interesará escuchar. Como has dicho, llegaste por primera vez, reconociste el terreno, fuiste a la sede del gobierno, tuviste reuniones con algunas personas, y no estuvieron muy dispuestas a escuchar. José A.: ¡Genial! Parece que mi charla estuvo muy buena. (Risas) Es la primera la charla TED con aclaración de la historia. Me siento tan bien... (Risas) NM: Cuéntanos cuáles fueron algunos de los retos, y cuándo percibiste que empezaban a recurrir a ti, a pedirte ayuda. JA: No podemos pedirle todo a la Cruz Roja o al Ejército de Salvación. Pero la idea es que yo he hecho donaciones a estas organizaciones en el pasado, y son organizaciones importantes y tal vez el problema es que esperamos demasiado de ellas. No es que no hicieron lo que tenían que hacer. El problema es la expectativa que tenemos de estas organizaciones. Pero en un momento como este no puedes de repente lavarte las manos, y decir que va a venir otro a arreglarlo. Teníamos un problema muy simple con una solución muy sencilla. No se trataba de un país lejano o la Zona Verde en Baghdad. Era EE. UU., un hermoso lugar llamado Puerto Rico, con cientos, miles de restaurantes y gente dispuesta a echar una mano, pero de pronto, teníamos gente hambrienta, y no teníamos ni idea de cómo servirles en el corto plazo. Y sí, FEMA, de alguna manera, pensaba cómo alimentar a esa gente. La Cruz Roja no tenía una buena solución, porque la Convención Bautista del Sur, el mayor banco de alimentos de EE. UU., mis héroes, nunca fueron convocados a Puerto Rico. Cuando la Cruz Roja reparte alimentos después de un huracán en EE. UU., en realidad es la Convención Bautista del Sur. Pero en Puerto Rico no pasó eso. El Ejército de Salvación pidió 420 platos una noche lluviosa de miércoles para un centro de ancianos. A mí me encanta ayudarles, pero según mi criterio, son ellos los que se supone que deberían ayudarnos a responder a esos gritos de auxilio. El jueves por la mañana me levanto preocupadísimo porque aún no habíamos pensado cómo íbamos a alimentar a la isla. Y algunos dirán que estoy haciendo el problema más grande de lo que era. Teníamos cientos y cientos de organizaciones tocando la puerta para pedirnos una bandeja de comida. Así que ahí está la prueba de que la pobreza era real. No podemos seguir alimentando a EE. UU. con comida preparada o algo que lo abres y... ya saben. Le di esa misma comida a los gatos, (Risas) y después les di pollo y arroz del que hicimos, y al final comían el pollo y el arroz. (Risas) (Aplausos) ¡No quisieron la otra comida! Se puede subsistir a base de eso durante un día, dos o cinco, pero esas comidas preparadas cuestan unos 12,14,15 o 20 dólares y las pagan los contribuyentes. Va bien en ciertas ocasiones, durante la guerra, pero no para alimentar a la población durante semanas y semanas, y más cuando se puede contratar a una empresa local privada para que haga el mismo trabajo, mucho mejor, creando puestos de trabajo, ayudando a la economía local a recuperarse, para que todo vuelva a la normalidad lo más rápido posible. Por eso empezamos a cocinar. Tú estabas ahí conmigo. Y por eso nos gastamos hasta el último dólar en las tarjetas. Si American Express nos está escuchando, un descuento no nos vendría mal. (Risas) O Visa. NM: ¿Cuál es la situación ahora? Ha pasado un mes, has dicho que ha habido algunas mejoras en San Juan y un foco de trabajo en las afueras, pero evidentemente aún quedan retos. ¿Qué es lo siguiente? JA: Lo siguiente es que de a poco empezamos a reducir el servicio, desde que la FEMA nos dijo más o menos que pensaban que ya tenían todo controlado y que no nos necesitaban más. Pero solo te crees las cosas hasta un cierto punto... Nos trasladamos del lugar que han visto, donde servíamos 60 000 platos, a otro, igual de grande, pero mejor localizado, y también más barato, donde vamos a cocinar entre 20 y 25 mil platos diarios. Y también dejamos montadas cuatro, cinco, seis cocinas estratégicamente ubicadas por la isla, en lo alto de las montañas, en las áreas pobres. Tenemos mucha información. Sabemos quién recibe el Programa Asistencial de Nutrición Suplementaria, los cupones para alimentos. Sabemos quién los tiene y quién los usa. Así que en las partes de la isla donde nadie los usa, esas son las zonas donde enfocamos nuestros esfuerzos. Es increíble cómo, a veces, tener información te da pistas sobre quiénes son los necesitados. Así que fuimos a la ciudad de Morovis. Preciosa. Tiene el mejor restaurante de pollo de la historia. Deberían ir a Morovis. DT: Suena bien. JA: Vi el pollo mientras llevaba unos sándwiches y paré. Iba con unos oficiales de la Seguridad Nacional. Paramos y comimos el pollo. Y luego nos fuimos a llevar los sándwiches a otro lugar llamado San Lorenzo. San Lorenzo estaba en crisis porque el puente se había caído entonces era una isla dentro de otra, una pequeña comunidad rodeada de agua. Todo el mundo nos decía: "¡Aquello es un desastre!". Entregamos los sándwiches, volví a Morovis y pensé: "¿Saben qué? Si es un "desastre", con sándwiches no alcanza". Compré 120 pollos, y yuca, y arroz, y volvimos al puente roto, cruzamos el río, con el agua hasta arriba por todos lados, llegamos con los 120 pollos, entregamos la comida, y muy agradecidos, nos dijeron: "Estamos bien, no precisamos más comida. Tenemos gas, tenemos dinero, tenemos buena comida y agua limpia también. Ocúpense de otras comunidades que lo necesitan más". ¿Ven? La comunicación es clave. En ocasiones como esta, podemos fiarnos de noticias falsas o podemos obtener información real para tomar decisiones inteligentes y ocuparnos de los verdaderos problemas. Y eso es lo que hacemos. (Aplausos) NM: Fue un trabajo increíble, y un placer ser testigo de primera mano y aportar un granito de arena. JA: Lo hiciste posible. NM: En un momento llegaste a cocinar cerca de 150 000 comidas al día, alrededor de la isla, lo que es realmente increíble. Y al mismo tiempo pienso que estableciste un modelo de cómo se puede hacer esto en el futuro. Creo que esa es la lección que nos enseña esto. DT: Claro. Esto es algo posible, que se puede reproducir. JA: Ah, pero voy a dejar de venir a las charlas TED, porque después Uds. piensan que cualquier cosa es posible. (Risas) Y después mi mujer me dirá: "Me dijiste que ibas a cocinar mil platos en un día, ¡no puedo dejarte solo un día!". (Risas) Pero espero que 'World Central Kitchen'... Ah, hay una cosa que hicimos que no les conté: levanté el teléfono y empecé a llamar gente. Gente que yo pensaba que tenía la experiencia para poder ayudarnos. así que llamé a una empresa llamada 'Bon Appétit, Fedele'. Bon Appétit es una empresa de comidas muy grande. Hacen comida para Google, y para los estadios, y cosas así. Tienen sede en California. Son parte de grupo más grande llamado 'Compass'. Y les dije: "¿Saben qué? Necesito cocineros que puedan cocinar grandes cantidades. Comida buena y de calidad, en grandes cantidades". En menos de 24 horas, conseguí gente y chefs que me ayudaron. En un momento dispuse de 16 de los mejores chefs de EE. UU. Es que EE. UU. es un país fraternal que siempre contribuye con lo mejor sí. Con los años hemos aprendido que estos chefs de EE. UU. tendrán un papel importante en el desarrollo de las actividades para alimentar EE. UU. y otros países en tiempos de hambruna. Lo que hay que empezar a hacer es llevar la experiencia adecuada a los lugares donde es necesaria. A veces tengo la sensación, como cuando fui a la FEMA, de que llevamos la experiencia inadecuada adonde ni siquiera es necesaria. Los de la FEMA son gente estupenda. Son inteligentes, están preparados, pero viven bajo esa asombrosa organización jerárquica piramidal donde todos caen por su propio peso. Hay que empoderar a la gente para que pueda alcanzar el éxito. Nosotros diseñamos un organigrama más llano en el que todos eran dueños de la situación y todos tomábamos decisiones rápidas, solucionando los problemas de inmediato. (Aplausos) DT: Definitivamente. Otro fuerte aplauso para José Andrés. (Aplausos)